<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A fruitfull sermon preached in Christs-Church the 13. of Iulie. Anno 1589. By Anthony Tyrell sometime a seminarie priest. But by the great mercie of God made a true professor of the Gospel, and preacher of his holy word: conteining an admonition vnto vertue, and a dehortation from vice. Taken by characterye</title>
            <author>Tyrrell, Anthony, 1552-1610?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1589</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 81 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 39 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A14157</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 24474</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S118810</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99854017</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99854017</idno>
            <idno type="VID">19423</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A14157)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 19423)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 552:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A fruitfull sermon preached in Christs-Church the 13. of Iulie. Anno 1589. By Anthony Tyrell sometime a seminarie priest. But by the great mercie of God made a true professor of the Gospel, and preacher of his holy word: conteining an admonition vnto vertue, and a dehortation from vice. Taken by characterye</title>
                  <author>Tyrrell, Anthony, 1552-1610?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[78] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Iohn Windet, and are to be sold at the signe of the Sun in Pauls church-yard by Abraham Kitson,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1589]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Publication date from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-E (-E8).</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: A fruitful sermon.</note>
                  <note>With a final colophon leaf.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  16th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:19423:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19423:1"/>
            <p>A FRVITFVLL SERMON PREACHED in Chriſts-Church the 13. of <hi>Iulie. Anno</hi> 1589. <hi>By</hi> Anthony Tyrell ſometime a Semi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie Prieſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But by the great mercie of God made</hi> a true profeſſor of the Goſpel, and <hi>Preacher of his holy word: contei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning</hi> an admonition vnto <hi>vertue, and a dehorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from vice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Taken by Characterye.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.21.</bibl> Better it had bin for a man not to haue knowen the way of righteouſnes, then after that hee hath knowen it, to turne from the holie commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement that was giuen vnto him.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>AT LONDON Printed by Iohn Windet, and are</hi> to be ſold at the ſigne of the <hi>Sun in Pauls church-yard</hi> by Abraham Kitſon.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:19423:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19423:2"/>
            <head>TO THE MOST reuerend Father in God <hi>Iohn Archb. of Canterb. his hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble</hi> Suppliant <hi>Anthonie Tyrell wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth aboundance of al ſpirituall graces,</hi> and bleſsings from God the Father, of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt both in this world, and in the world to come.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>
               </hi> Stood in doubt ſomwhile (Right Reuerende and my eſpeciall good Lord) whether I might preſume to make dedication of ſo ſimple and ſlender a matter vnto your graue and learned Grace: but knowing how much I ſtood bound vnto your great and exceeding charitie: and conſidering with what fauour you do affect a ſimple and well meaning minde, and how reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giouſlie you haue proſecuted my irreligi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous demeanor, in receiuing me as a loſt &amp; ſtraied ſheepe vnto the fold of Chriſt againe, and waying therewithal, that
<pb facs="tcp:19423:3"/>notwithſtanding my true and vnfained returne, yet euerie ſleight action of mine may ſeriouſlie be Cenſured of ſuch as are not giuen to ſpeake the beſt, but en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clined to iudge the worſt, I thought it expedient for mine owne comfort to flie vnto your Lordſhips patronage, and I hope for the cauſes before conſidered that I may boldlie do it without preſumption, not doubting but that thereby I ſhal ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie be defended from the ſiniſter opinion of all my aduerſaries.</p>
            <p>May it pleaſe you therefore to vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe to accept this ſimple Sermon, which for the vtilitie of many, and for the hurt of none I haue cauſed to be publiſhed in printe, a matter though ſmall in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, yet great in good will, and the grateful acceptance therof at your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips handes may be an incouragement to greater endeuours. It was not my pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe and meaning at the firſt to put this forth in print, but vppon an occaſion as your Lordſhip may vnderſtand in the
<pb facs="tcp:19423:3"/>Preface, and ſince it hath ſo fallen out that I did determine it to come abroad, I thought I could not do better then to ſhroud it vnder the couert of your wings.</p>
            <p>And in an other reſpect I am glad that the occaſion hath bin offered me to ſet this foorth in publike, that withall I might publiſh vnto the world yet once a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine the conſtancie of my faith, which by reaſon of my former inconſtancy hath bin hardly Cenſured of manie as well Proteſtantes as Papiſtes. The Papiſt thinking that I was aſhamed of my late publicke action at Paules Croſſe, and the Proteſtant thinking that I did it but diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblinglie. To the firſt I anſwere with the Apoſtle S. <hi>Paul. Non erubeſco Euangelium:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. 1.16.</note> 
               <hi>Eſt enim virtus Dei in ſalutem omni credenti.</hi> I am not aſhamed of the Goſpel, for it is the power of God vnto ſaluation to all beleeuers. And to the other I do anſwere with our Sauiour. <hi>Nolite iudicare,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 7.1.2</note> 
               <hi>vt non iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicemini: in quo enim iudicio iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicaueritis,
<pb facs="tcp:19423:4"/>iudicabimini.</hi> Iudge yee not, that yeè be not iudged: For with what iudgement you do iudge, you ſhall be iudged. And therefore leauing the true diſcuſsion thereof vnto the euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting Iudge that knoweth the ſecrets of all mens hartes, and ſhall lay open to all the world in the latter day the priuitie of a mans conſcience, I will ſay no more but this, that I may ſatisfie him that ſtandeth in doubt of me, if I can. That I do profeſſe my ſelfe to be no otherwiſe in hart, ſoule, and conſcience, then I do ſet downe here by pen, namelie a true ſeruant of Ieſus Chriſt, one that hath bin by his mercie called and reclaimed from the floods of errors, Idolatrie, and ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition, wherewith I haue bin hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ouerwhelmed, and that mine eies are opened, and do behold my Lord and Sauiour Chriſt Ieſus in his Goſpel, and do receaue &amp; imbrace him in his word, and that I obey and ſerue him in that true maner &amp; forme that he hath pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed
<pb facs="tcp:19423:4"/>in the ſame. And that I do from my hart, as I haue heretofore teſtified, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquiſh and abandon the Pope and the ſea of Rome ſo far forth as it mainteineth Idolatrie, fauoureth ſuperſtition, nouri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth ſchiſme and deuiſion, teacheth diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedience both to God and Princes. And I do renounce him for Gods Vicar on earth, which rebelleth againſt the Lord in Heauen, in ouerthrowing kingdoms, murdering of annointed Princes, remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing ſubiectes from their due and natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall obedience, and all to mainteine him ſelfe in pride and Antichriſtian gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, acknowledging no other Church but the vniuerſall Church of Chriſt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſed throughout the world, nor any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hed of the ſame then Chriſt Ieſus, by the merits of whoſe paſsion I hope to be ſaued, and in whoſe faith I purpoſe to liue and die.</p>
            <p>This being my publicke and outward teſtimonie, yet once againe by this occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion vttered, I hope all good and Godly
<pb facs="tcp:19423:5"/>men will reſt fullie ſatisfied, and as for the mouthes of the vngodlie in time the Lord ſhall ſtop them.</p>
            <p>I needed not (my good Lord) vnto your Paternity haue vſed this proteſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and yet I hope the renewal thereof with the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinuance ſhalbe no ſmal com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort vnto you, who thirſteth the health of my ſoule as your owne.</p>
            <p>The cauſe chieflie why I did it, was to ſtoppe the tongues of ſuch as are alwaies itching to hurt and preiudice other men. I haue ſaid my minde, it reſteth that I pray for them, to graunt me patience to beare the rebuke, and that I may haue grace to remaine irreprouable vnto the end: for the which I doubt not but your Lordſhip of your Charitie will vouchſafe to ſay Amen.</p>
            <p>To trouble your Lordſhip farther by way of Preface I thought not neede: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore beſeeching your Grace to pardon my bold attempt, to accept of my poore ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour, I conclude, praying God continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>allie
<pb facs="tcp:19423:5"/>to bleſſe you, to make you a carefull and vigilant Paſtour ouer his flocke, to endue you with all graces neceſſarie for the gouernment of the ſame. And ſo kiſsing the hand of your Paternity, with all humilitie I take my leaue. From my chamber in London. Nouemb. <hi>1589.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Graces moſt humble and daily Oratour.</hi> Anthony Tyrell</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:19423:6"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19423:6"/>
            <head>To the Chriſtian Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T was not my mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning I muſt confeſſe trulie (Good Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Reader) to haue this ſhort and briefe exortation which I made for my priuate exerciſe to come forth thus in publicke, partlie for that I know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing mine owne ignorance and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> might ſeeme a great deale more bold then wiſe to ſet forth ſo ſimple and ſlender an action vnto the view of wiſe and learned men, and partlie leaſt I might be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of manie, either for want of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion in not iudging of ſpirituall actions more maturely and ſoberly, or that I gaped after vaine glorie, which would condemne mee of greater follie among al Godlie me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but chieflie for that I had no iuſt or good occaſion to induce me to the ſame. The cauſe therefore why it
<pb facs="tcp:19423:7"/>is come forth, in briefe was this. At the time I made my exhortation publicklie in Chriſt his Church in London, my wordes were no ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner out of my mouth but a yong youth had penned my Sermon <hi>ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>batim</hi> by Characterie, an art newly inuented. It was this youthes plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, for the manifeſting of his ſkill in that ſwift kind of writing, to pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh my Sermon in print, yet hone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtlie he came vnto me, to enforme me firſt of the matter. Hee was to me a meere ſtraunger, of whom, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter I had vnderſtood his intent and purpoſe, I craued reſpite to pauſe of the matter before I would giue my conſent. I conſidered firſt of my ſelfe what might be thought or ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, &amp; rather I ſhould be eſteemed fooliſh and vainglorious tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue commendation of anie man. Secondlie that the youth did it but to ſhew his ſkill and cunning in the
<pb facs="tcp:19423:7"/>dexte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of his owne handewriting, and that it was not ſimply for the health of ſoules or ſpirituall profite of any man, and after I had debated thus to &amp; fro with my ſelfe, I was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined to haue ſtaied his copie, and to haue let all alone. Yet reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring my ſelfe, that the workes of the Lorde are wonderful, and that he vſeth ſuch means for bringing of thinges to paſſe which are verie ſtrange and to me vnknowen, That the matter might perhaps be profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table vnto ſome, that whereas I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing but newly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerted, &amp; of many ſuſpected for my ſynceritie in reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, it might bee an occaſion to giue ſome farther teſtimonie then I haue done, and that ſome thinges it may pleaſe the Lord to worke by this ſimple actio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for the benefite of his Church, which vnto me was vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowen, I altered my purpoſe and intent, ſo far forth as I would not
<pb facs="tcp:19423:8"/>be iudge of mine owne doing, but commit it to ſome other. I did write my letters therefore vnto a graue &amp; learned man, I told him what had happened, and I ſet downe mine owne miſlike, for feare that thinges might not be well &amp; orderly done, ſubiecting my ſelfe and my matter vnto his vertuous, wiſe, and learned cenſure. It pleaſed him to returne me my copy again approued: what ſhould I do? ſhould I conceale it? ſo I might perhaps contriſtate the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Spirite. For the comming of it forth might yeelde perhaps ſome deuout and penitent ſoule ſome comfort and profite. For thy ſake therefore (good Chriſtian Reader) who ſo euer thou art, without all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther reſpect I haue permitted this ſle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der endeuor of mine to come to light, in hope that although I may be ſubiect vnto blame of manie, yet I may do ſome good therby to few.
<pb facs="tcp:19423:8"/>To teach them how they ought to deteſt and hate ſinne, to walke wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>relie before the face of the Lord, that receiuing the manifold graces &amp; mercies at his hands, they be not vngrateful, &amp; hauing once throwne out the foule ſpirit of ſinne out of their ſoules by true repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tance, they permit him not to returne again by their great fault and negligence, for if they do, what will follow thereof they ſhall vnderſtand by the future diſcourſe. Thus hauing giuen thee a full ſatisfaction of the cauſe of the publiſhing of this preſent diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, I am to admoniſh but one other thing, and ſo I end. He that penned my Sermon as I vttered it in Pulpit, did it moſt exactly, writing it word for word: Yet when I per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued that it ſhould come to the print, I did onely peruſe it againe, altering ſome words, but nothing of the matter: and thus much I
<pb facs="tcp:19423:9"/>thought good to aduertiſe, leaſt they that heard me when I pronou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced it, ſhould thinke it was not the ſame, but ſome other. And this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all that I am to ſay at this time by way of preface, if any ſpirituall comfort redound thereby vnto thy ſoule, Gods name be glorified, and it is all that I require: and ſo I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit thee vnto the Lord, &amp; my ſelfe to thy good prayer. From my cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber in London. 1589. 1. Nouemb.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Thy faithfull Brother, and fellow-labourer in Chriſt,</hi> Anthony Tyrell.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:19423:9"/>
            <head>A FRVITFVLL SERMON CONTEI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the nature and vilenes of <hi>ſin, preached at Chriſt</hi> his Church, by <hi>Anthony Tyrell.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>Math. Chap. 12. verſ. 43.44.45.</bibl>
               <q>When the vnclean ſpirit is gon out of a man, he walketh throughout drie places, ſeeking reſt, and findeth none. Then he ſaith, I wil returne into my houſe, from whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce I came out. And when hee is come, he findeth it emptie, ſwept, and garniſhed. Then goeth he &amp; taketh 7. ſpirites worſe then himſelfe, and they enter in and dwell there. And the laſt ſtate of that man is worſe then the firſt. Euen ſo ſhall it bee alſo vnto this froward generation.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE</hi> Occaſion of theſe our Sauiour his wordes (Right Worſhipfull and deerly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued in our Lord and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour Ieſus Chriſt) of diuers men is diuerſlie conſidered. Some thinke that they are generallie ment of the whole multitude of the Iewes, who after they
<pb facs="tcp:19423:10"/>had receiued the law of Moſes (being brought out of Egipt when the Deuils had poſſeſſed them with great blindnes and ſuperſtition) and were taught a pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar and true manner of worſhipping the Lord according to his holie wil and pleaſure,<note place="margin">Exod. 20.</note> that then the Deuil departed from the Iewes and trauelled drie and deſert places, neuer reſting vntil hee came among the Gentiles, whom hee corrupted in ſuch vile and groſſe man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, as looſing both common ſence, hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane reaſon and vnderſtanding, they fel into all blindnes, idolatrie, and ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition, and wallowed and continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the ſame vntill ſuch time as our Lord and Sauiour was incarnate, and preached the truth of his holie Goſpell among them, the which glad tidinges the Gentlies embraced, beleeuing in Chriſt Ieſus and forſaking the groſſe errours, whereas the Iewes, vnto who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the promiſe moſt properlie belonged, &amp; to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Meſſias peculiarly was promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, remained moſt obſtinate,<note place="margin">Gen. 12.3 18.18.</note> and wold neither receiue him or beleeue in him. Sathan then with all the foule troupe
<pb facs="tcp:19423:10"/>of his filthie familie being caſt out of the Gentiles by the faith they had in Ieſus Chriſt, and hauing then no reſt, ſaid hee would returne vnto the place from whence he came, namelie to the vncredulous Iewes, and finding their Synagogue empty, that is the Scribes, Phariſes, and principal teachers of the Law to be void of faith, to contradict al that they might Ieſus Chriſt who was come into the world for their ſaluation and comfort, and that it was alſo gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, that is to ſay, ſtuffed and filled with a number of blinde ceremonies, &amp; phariſaicall traditions contrarie vnto that that the Lord had either taught or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, in ſo much as our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour pronounced his terrible woes, as you may read at large in <hi>S. Math.</hi> Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel.<note place="margin">Mat. 24.</note> The deuil (I ſay) finding this opor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunitie and aduantage, returneth backe vnto them againe, &amp; repoſſeſſeth them, taking ſeauen ſpirites with him worſe then himſelfe, in ſo much as the end is become much worſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the beginning, they being now in farder bondage and captiuitie then euer they were vnder
<pb facs="tcp:19423:11"/>
               <hi>Pharao,</hi> hauing no proper countrie, or place to remaine or abide in, but are made vagabonds throughout the world; as it appeareth plainlie of them at this day: and well may it be ſaid that their end is worſe then their beginning, for better it had bin that Chriſt had neuer bin incarnat, then being incarnat, they wil not now receiue him.</p>
            <p>Other ſome applye theſe our Sauiour his wordes as ſpoken of heretikes, who being of Infidels and Pagans, by the mercie of Chriſt made Chriſtians, and the Deuil expelled from them by faith in Ieſus Chriſt, and falling againe by Apoſtacie into hereſie or infidelitie, the Deuill returneth to make his reentrie again, bringing with him ſeauen worſe then himſelfe, and repoſſeſſeth them, &amp; then it commeth to paſſe that their ende is worſe then the beginning, for of an infidell there remaineth ſome hope that he may be conuerted and beleeue, but of an apoſtate, or an obſtinate heretike there is ſcarſe anie hope at all. Although this application be not amiſſe, yet here it agreeth not with the litterall ſence.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:19423:11"/>
            <p>Other ſome therfore (and they in my iudgement come neerer to the letter) thinke that theſe wordes of our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our wer directly ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto the Scribes and Phariſes, who ſeeing &amp; beholding the wonderfull miracles that our Lord and Sauiour had wrought, and namely that, notable miracle y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> is mentioned in this preſent Chapiter,<note place="margin">Math. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 22.</note> of the man that was both blind and dumb, out of whom our Sauiour did caſt out a Deuill, and by the power of his Godhead made him both to ſee and to ſpeake, whereupon the common multitude ſeeing &amp; behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding it, forthwith glorified and magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed God, but the Scribes and Phariſes, who ought to haue had more knowledge and vnderſtanding, became thereby more malitious and obſtinate, and theſe miracles that could not come but by the power of the Deuinitie, moſt blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouſly they did attribute them to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede from the power of Sathan, ſaying that through the power of Beelzebub the prince of deuils he did caſt out other deuils.<note place="margin">Math. 1.24.</note> Whereuppon after Chriſt had defended him ſelfe and proued inuinci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly,
<pb facs="tcp:19423:12"/>the power of his Godhead by an ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument of of a kingdome deuided againſt it ſelfe that it cannot long ſtand,<note place="margin">Math. 12.5.</note> &amp; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of concluding, that if Sathan were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided againſt Sathan, then his king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome could not ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, but ſhould in ſhort time be conſumed and ouer throwen. In the ende he addeth theſe wordes that I haue recited for my text, whereby hee proueth that thoſe miracles that he had wrought amongſt them ſhould ſerue for their farder condemnation, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth by that example of an vncleane ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite going forth, how he returneth with more ſtrength backe againe, and repoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſing them from whom bee departed maketh their ende to be worſe then the beginning, and therefore the concluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on was, that the ſtate of thoſe Scribes &amp; Phariſes was now much worſe than if no miracles had bin wrought amongſt them, or grace offered vnto them.</p>
            <p>Finally it is thought, &amp; not vnprobable, that theſe our Sauioure his wordes were particularlye directed vnto that man,<note place="margin">Mat. 12. v. 22.</note> out of whom he had caſt the deuil, and to whom hee had reſtored both his
<pb facs="tcp:19423:12"/>ſpeech and his ſight, that hauing recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued theſe benefites and graces at the Lords handes, he ſhould not become ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vngratefull or vnthankefull, or by thinking himſelfe ſecure, liue any thing the more looſely, but to walk before the Lord with al humilitie, feare and cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſpection, leaſt by ouermuch, negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence or miſdemeanour the deuil ſhould returne backe againe, and ſo alleaging that exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple ſhould ſhew, that if it chaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced ſo to fall out, his end would become much worſe then his beginning. The like caueat or warning our Sauiour gaue vnto the diſeaſed man whom hee cured at the poole of <hi>Betheiſda,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Io. 5. v. 2.</note> whom hee finding in the temple ſaid vnto him, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">verſe. </seg>14</label> behold thou art made whole: ſinne no more leaſt a worſe thing come vnto thee. This caueat might alſo ſerue for the ſtanders by, and may ſerue alſo for vs at this time, and make vs ſo much y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> more happie, if by other mens harms we can learne to beware.</p>
            <p>Hauing (as I think) ſaid ſo much as may be for the vnderſtanding of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the letter, and of the end and
<pb facs="tcp:19423:13"/>ſcope whereunto our Sauiour vttered the forementioned wordes. It reſteth now that for our particular vtilitie and profite that ſhall either heare or reade them, wee may vnderſtand what bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite we are to take by them, and the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefite will be this, if we make it an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample vnto our ſelues, for that it may ſerue verie wel, for ſo much as there is none of vs all but haue receiued innu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merable benefites and graces at the Lordes hands, more then mind can co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue, or tongue can vtter, for all which if we ſhould ſhew our ſelues vngrate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, as that man did, the Deuil hauing bin once alreadie by Gods grace caſt out of vs, might returne againe, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning againe bring other ſeaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> worſe then himſelfe, and then woe vnto each of vs, for our end ſhould be much worſe then our beginning.</p>
            <p>Wherefore, for memorie and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods ſake I ſhal deuide y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whole matter into <hi>4.</hi> partes. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> In the firſt I wil ſhew how Sathan departeth from the ſoule of man or woman, and how hee demea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth himſelfe when he is departed. In
<pb facs="tcp:19423:13"/>the ſecond I will ſhew the preſumption of Sathan in returning againe to ſee if he can make any reentrance into that man or woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> from whom he went out of; <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> and therewithal I ſhal ſhew the cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes that moue the Deuil to make re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entrance. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> In the third I will ſhew how ſtrongly he reentreth and maketh the place whereinto he is ſo entered his habitation or dwelling place. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Fourthly and laſtlie I will ſhew how the ende of that man ſo repoſſed is worſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the beginning, with the reaſons and cauſes.</p>
            <p>As touching the firſt which is the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uils departure and his demeanour after he is departed, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Part </seg>1</label> it is conteined in theſe wordes. <hi>When an vnclean ſpirite is gon out of a man, he walketh drie &amp; deſert places ſeeking reſt, and findeth none.</hi> In theſe wordes is conteined both his departure &amp; demeanour. Now to come vnto euerie thing in order you muſt firſt conſider what is ment by an vncleane ſpirite. This word ſpirite is in holy Scripture indifferently taken, ſometime it ſignifieth the holie ſpirite which is the third perſon in Trinitie,
<pb facs="tcp:19423:14"/>ſometime it ſignifieth the ſoule of man, ſometime the aire, or y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> life of any crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. When ſo euer you ſhall reade or finde in holie ſcripture this word ſpirit, ſet downe ſimplie without any other word to expreſſe the meaning therof, it is commonly taken in the better part, as when <hi>S. Paul</hi> in the <hi>5.</hi> to the <hi>Gal.</hi> rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>koneth vp the fruites of the ſpirite, na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming them,<note place="margin">Gal. 5.22.</note> Charitie, Ioy, Peace, and the like, it is ment there of the holie ſpirit.<note place="margin">Rom. 8.26</note> And in the <hi>8.</hi> to the <hi>Rom.</hi> where he ſaith, the ſpirite helpeth our infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and the like; he meaneth alſo of the holy ſpirit. But being ſet down with his adiectiue, the nature &amp; qualitie of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> adie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiue wil ſhew what thing y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tiue is, as when it is ſaid, holie ſpirit, good ſpirit, or the like. Likewiſe the Deuil who is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wicked ſpirite is alwayes cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly ſet down by his adiectiue, as in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſt of <hi>Sam.</hi> the <hi>15.</hi> chap. it is ſaid y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> euil ſpirit vexed or tormented <hi>Saul;</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Sam. 15. v. 15. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>t 12.</note> wherby is ment the Deuil. And likewiſe here in this place our Sauiour naming an vncleane ſpirit, he meaneth the deuill.</p>
            <p>Now that wee vnderſtand what ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit
<pb facs="tcp:19423:14"/>is ſpoken of or ment in this place, it followeth that we vnderſtand why hee is called vncleane.</p>
            <p>The Deuill being a ſpirit, as he is the creature of God hee was created in great excellencie, for there was nothing that the Lord had made which he appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued not to be verie good, as may appeare in the firſt of <hi>Geneſis.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 1. v. 31.</note> And eſpeciallie the Angels who were of all other crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures the moſt noble. But <hi>Lucifer</hi> the chiefe of the Angels not being content with thoſe excellent giftes of nature which the Lord had beſtowed on him, but aſpiring vnto the maieſtye of God, &amp; vſurping (as it were) the glorie of his deuinitie, was therfore worthilie deiec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and ſo manie as conſented vnto him, &amp; became of all creatures the moſt vile and abominable, not vile in nature but in condition and qualitie, for being caſt downe into eternal miſerie himſelf irreparable without all redemption, he endeuoureth all that hee may to make man in as bad eſtate as him ſelfe, and that he can not do but in tempting him to ſinne: the which being a vile and an
<pb facs="tcp:19423:15"/>abhominable thing in the ſight of the Lord, and a thing moſt impure and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean vnbeſeeming the nature and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of Angell or man, and for that he laboureth continually, tempting vs to bring vs into this impurity, the deuil is ſaid to be an vnclean ſpirite, vnclean (I ſay) by operation, not by creation.</p>
            <p>This vnclean ſpirite being departed from a man. It followeth to know how and in what maner he departeth. Sure and certaine it is that the vncleane ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit Sathan neuer departeth from man or woman by his good will, for ſuch is the enuie and malice that hee beareth vnto man, that he neuer ceaſeth labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to bring him vnto eternall deſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as witneſſeth <hi>S. Pet.</hi> in his firſt epiſt. <hi>5.</hi> Chap. verſe. <hi>8.</hi> ſaying.<note place="margin">1 Fet. 5.8.</note> Be yee ſober &amp; vigilant, for your aduer ſarie the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uil goeth about like a roaring Lion ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king whom he may deuour, whom you muſt reſiſt being ſtrong in faith: ſurely he goeth about continuallie watching &amp; prying where hee may get a pray, and ſuch is the malice and hatred that hee beareth towards man, Firſt in reſpect
<pb facs="tcp:19423:15"/>that he is created vnto the image and ſimilitude of God, to poſſeſſe that place from whence hee is deiected, and in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the curſe that was giuen him in Paradiſe,<note place="margin">Gen. 3.</note> and that it was told him that the ſeede of the woman ſhould bruſe his hed, that he proſecuteth mankind with an implacable hatred, and ſeeketh to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy vs all that he can. By his good will therefore he neuer departeth from vs, and hee tarieth or abideth with no man for any goodnes, but to bring him to miſchiefe or deſtruction. Euerie man therefore that is in ſin, he is accompted to poſſeſſe: for ſo manie as are wilfull &amp; obſtinate ſinners, they are vnder the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uils ſubiection. If any man be called from his ſinne by the grace and mercy of God and true repentance, then the deuil is ſaid to depart, which departure, (as I ſaid) it is not of the deuils accord, but by the force of Gods Spirite that expelleth him by true repentance out of a ſinners hart, for other wiſe he would neuer depart: And therefore Sathan, of our Lord and Sauiour in holy ſcripture is called <hi>Inimicus homo,</hi> that is,<note place="margin">Mat. 13. v. 28</note> the
<pb facs="tcp:19423:16"/>enemie by a kinde of ſingularitie, for that there is no enemie comparable vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him in hatred that ſeeketh the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction and loſſe of our bodie and ſoule for euermore, Yet as enuious as he is, and as malitious, he dwelleth no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger or abideth in vs more then wee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine in ſin, &amp; ſo ſoone as it pleaſeth the Lord to cal vs by his grace vnto repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, wil he, nil he, he muſt depart away from vs, for ſure and certaine it is, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the rules in Logick, two con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traries can not agree at one time toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in one ſubiect, but as vertue com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth in, vice muſt goe out, and as grace appeareth, ſin fleeth, and where the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſpirite taketh poſſeſſion, the vncleane ſpirite muſt packe out. I followeth, <hi>When an vnclean ſpirite is gon out of a man, he walketh, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hetherto hath bin diſcuſſed ſo much as I thought neceſſarie for the time &amp; place, what the vncleane ſpirite is, how he departeth from a man, it commeth now in order to ſhew, his demeanour is to walke throughout drie places.</p>
            <p>The walking of Sathan through drie
<pb facs="tcp:19423:16"/>places is but a metaphor taken from a drye ground wherein is no moiſture of water whereby it can yeeld or bring forth any fruite, for as almightie God hath his orchard and vineyard that brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth foorth good fruit, ſo the deuil hath his orchard and vineyard to bring forth fruite agreeable vnto his appetite. The fruite that the deuil gapeth after is noo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther but the ſpoile and deſtruction of man, which he proueth by his temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and the corruptions of our fleſh: &amp; firſt hee ſeeketh to deſtroy the ſoule of man, being ſure y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> if once he can come to the poſſeſſion of the ſoule that the bodie wil come after, &amp; if by Gods mercie he be prohibited that he can not hurt vs in ſouls, then he laboureth all that he can to plague and aflict vs in bodie, If he can not in bodie, then in our temporall goods, if not in our goods, then in any thing that belongeth to the helth &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of man, as birdes of the ayre, fyſhes in the ſea, plantes, hearbes and trees, beaſts or any other cattel. And if by the permiſſion of God he be not ſuffered to hurt vs in any of theſe, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he is ſayd to
<pb facs="tcp:19423:17"/>to walke drie and deſert places then, is in places where he can make no fruite: for all thoſe labours of his hée acounteth fruitles wherin he may do no maner of miſchiefe either to man him ſelfe, or to the thinges that belong to man. And thus you know now what it is to walk in drie and deſert places. It followeth, <hi>Seeking reſt, and findeth none.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What reſt thinke you is that that the Deuill ſeeketh? Is it poſſible that Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than the enemy of God, and mortal ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my of man ſhould haue any reſt? doth he ſeeke to be reconciled vnto God, or to leaue tempting of man? can he euer bée at any reſt that carrieth alwaies his hel about him? no ſuch matter. The reſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Sathan ſéeketh is no more then how hee may accompliſh his malitious minde, &amp; put his deuiliſh practices in execution: Euen as a man that is giuen to wrath and enuie, who neuer is at quiet vntill he haue reuenged himſelfe, or ſhewen his malice vpon him that he perſecuted with hatred, and then he ſéemeth in that degrée to be at reſt, ſo is the Deuil is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted to bée at reſt when hee hath
<pb facs="tcp:19423:17"/>brought his malitious minde vnto any deuiliſh accompliſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t or execution: ſo manie ſoules as the Deuill can bring by any wicked ſuggeſtion or ſyniſter means vnto deſtruction, ſo much myſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe as he may vtter againſt any man or woman, ſo much reſt hée taketh in the accompliſhment of his wil, although otherwiſe he ſuſteine grieuous torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts and puniſhment at the Lords handes for the ſame, wherefore euerie man or woman is here to take héede that they make not themſelues like vnto the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uil in this point, as all they vndoubted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie do that do beare with themſelues re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenging mindes, and neuer are at qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et vntil they trouble or vex their neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, or haue taken reuengement on their enemie, who ſo euer doth ſo, doubtleſſe hee ſheweth himſelfe to bee the childe of Sathan, and if hee ſéeke, after Sathan for ſuch reſt, he ſhall haue that reſt that Sathan hath that is, to be tormented with the intollerable pains of hell fire for euermore, and neuer ſhal he come to any other reſt, much leſſe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to that reſt that is prepared for the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren
<pb facs="tcp:19423:18"/>of God to liue and remain in eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall bliſſe for euermore. And thus much of Sathans departure and his demea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour in ſéeking reſt and finding none. It followeth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Then he ſaith,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pars 2.</note> 
               <hi>I will returne into my houſe from whence I came out, and when he is come, he findeth it emptie, ſwept and garniſhed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is the ſecond part wherein I purpoſed to note vnto you the preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Deuils returne, ſaying I will returne into my houſe from whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce I came: and when he is come what cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes he findeth to force him make a reen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie, and they are three, namelie, that the houſe is emptie, that it is ſwept, and garniſhed. I wil entreat brieflie of eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry point in order.</p>
            <p>Firſt the Deuil hauing departed and walked drie and deſert places, ſéeking reſt and finding none, he ſayth that hée wil return vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> houſe from whence he came. Here is to be noted the boldnes &amp; the malice of Sathan, let him be expel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led and repulſed neuer ſo much, yet hée will returne againe: whereby we are
<pb facs="tcp:19423:18"/>taught neuer to bée too ſecure or voide of feare, but alwaies to ſtand vpon our gard, for as faſt as one temptatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> goeth, an other commeth, ſo ſone as one miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie is paſſed, forthwith commeth an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, a man neuer remaineth (as <hi>Iob</hi> ſaith) long in one eſtate,<note place="margin">Iob. 14. v. 2.</note> but now are we merie, and by and by ſad, now rich, then poore, now frée, by and by oppreſſed with temptation againe. I wil returne (ſaith he) vnto my houſe from whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce I came. The ſoule of that man or woman that the Deuil poſſeſſed for ſin, and by grace was expelled out, the deuil calleth his houſe, not his properlie by creation, for ſo euery man or woman is properly the Lords, for hee hath made vs,<note place="margin">Pſal. 95.</note> and not we our ſelues: but the Deuil calleth the ſoule of a ſinner his houſe by poſſeſſion, for ſo long as we remaine in the eſtate of grace, wée are the children of God, and our bodies are the temples of the holy Ghoſt, but ſo ſoone as wée giue our ſelues ouer vnto ſin, forthwith we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the ſlaues of Sathan, and our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies are made an habitatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and a recep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacle for Deuils. Here would be noted
<pb facs="tcp:19423:19"/>the dignitie of man or woman the fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord and y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> walketh in his waies how he is the temple of the holy Ghoſt. and the indignitie of euerie ſinner that maketh him ſelfe the bondſlaue of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than, and a receptacle of foule and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clane ſpirites. <hi>I will goe into my houſe from whence I came</hi> out. The Deuill deſireth rather to goe vnto his owne houſe that he poſſeſſed before, then to a ſtrange houſe which before was none of his: euery wicked ſpirite hath his proper houſe, the ſpirite of pride he har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boureth in the proud man, the ſpirite of Enuie in the enuious man, the ſpirit of Glotony and dronkennes in the Gloton or dronkard, the ſpirite of vncleannes in the vnchaſt and fleſhly man, the ſpirite of couetouſnes in the couetous man and vſurer, and ſo conſequently euery ſinne hath his proper and peculiar ſpirite.</p>
            <p>Now when he ſaith: <hi>I wil goe into my houſe from whence I came.</hi> Euery ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite ſéeketh to goe into his owne houſe, into that houſe whereof in former time he had poſſeſſion, out of the which hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, that is, out of the ſoules of ſinners,
<pb facs="tcp:19423:19"/>theſe foule and vncleane ſpirites by the mercie of God haue bin caſt out, ſome of Glottons and Dronkardes, being made ſober and temperate, ſome of en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uious men béeing made méeke and cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable, ſome of prowde men being made humble, ſome of fornicatours and adulterers being now made chaſt, ſome of couetous perſons being made liberal and charitable, and ſo of the like.</p>
            <p>Thus haue you heard the Deuils bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and preſumption, to put you in a warines and good caution, now let vs come to the cauſes that he findeth for his reentrance.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>After that the vncleane ſpirite was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned, hee founde his houſe emptie, ſwept &amp; garniſhed.</hi> Thrée cauſes ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to make him make reentrance, he watched his time and oportunity, &amp; ſo ſoon as any occaſion was giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, he plieth him, he looſeth it not, but takes it for his moſt aduantage. It ſtandeth therfore déerely beloued vs vppon to haue a vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gilant and watchfull eie vnto all the partes of our ſoule, to rule and gouerne well all the ſences of our bodie, all the
<pb facs="tcp:19423:20"/>motions and deſires of the minde, and eſpecially to preſerue our hart pure and cleane from the conſenting vnto any corruption or ſinne. <hi>Omni cuſtodia cuſtodi cor tuum</hi> (ſaith <hi>Salomon</hi>) <hi>quia ex ipſo vita procedit:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 4.23.</note> With all dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ece kéepe wel thy hart, for out of it procée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth life. Three cauſes or occaſions the vnclean ſpirit fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d out in this wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched perſon which gaue him means to reenter againe. The firſt wherof was, for that he found his houſe emptie. The ſoule of that man from whom Sathan was expelled remained empty: what is it to be empty? To bée emptie is to bée voide of faith, and he that is empty and void of faith, it can not be but he muſt be emptie alſo of al good workes. For I do not here diſtinguiſh faith from good works, as the Papiſtes commonly do, for when I ſpeake of faith I meane a iuſtifying faith which can not be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out good woorkes, no more then life can remaine in a mans bodie without a ſoule. I meane not a dead faith, or a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiliſh faith,<note place="margin">Iac. 2.</note> ſuch a faith as <hi>S. Iames</hi> doth mention in his Epiſt. This iuſtifying
<pb facs="tcp:19423:20"/>faith (I ſay) who ſo euer hath not, hée is emptie no doubt of all goodnes, &amp; with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out that faith as <hi>S. Paul</hi> ſaith <hi>11.</hi> to the <hi>Hebr. verſ. 6.</hi> It is impoſſible to pleaſe God. This emptineſſe of faith,<note place="margin">Heb. 11.6.</note> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently of all good workes, procéedeth of a kind of idlenes which is the mother and nurſe of all kinde of miſchiefe, and him I account to bee idle, that is not well occupied, for all ſuch as occupye themſelues in vaine and triſtinge buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, as in carding, dicing, vnlawfull gamings or exerciſes, (vnleſſe it be for an honeſt &amp; moderat recreation) I ſay) thoſe labours are no better the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> idlenes, for that they be childiſh, there is no pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit in them. And ſuch actions or labours which conteine in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> manifeſt and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parant euil, I ſay thoſe are deuilliſh, &amp; worſe then if a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> were childiſhly occu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pied or ydle altogether. That ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man that wanteth a true and perfect faith, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is fruitful by good works, can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer be wel occupied. It is not inough for a man by faith to apprehend Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus our Sauiour, as he is mercifull, as he hath redéemed vs, and payd for vs
<pb facs="tcp:19423:21"/>y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> price of our rede<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ption, but we muſt ap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>prehend him alſo as he is iuſt, as he ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth ſin, crutifiing it in his owne fleſh, and conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ning it in vs, and vs for ſin: we muſt apprehend him as he is riſen againe from death to life, with whom wée muſt alſo ariſe againe from death to life,<note place="margin">Coloſ. 3.</note> by dying to the world, and liuing vnto him by crucifying old <hi>Adam</hi> with all his concupiſcences, and putting on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> new, in iuſtice and righteouſnes, for he that is not partaker of the firſt reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, which is to riſe from ſinne to grace, ſhall neuer be partaker of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, to riſe from death to euerlaſting life. Let vs not therefore deceaue our ſelues with the bare name and title of faith,<note place="margin">2. Pet. c. 1. v. 10.</note> but let vs rather as <hi>Peter</hi> ſayth, by good workes endeuour to make our vocation and election certaine. Let vs alwaies be working and labouring like good and painfull ſeruantes in the vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard of the Lord, euery man in his vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation. That we ſhould ſo do, we are admoniſhed by that wéekly labour that the children of Iſrael had in the deſert, where euery day by the commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb facs="tcp:19423:21"/>of the Lord they were co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded to gather Manna,<note place="margin">Exod. 16.</note> onely the Sabaoth they ſhould reſt. Surely ſo with vs, we ought all the wéeke daies of this our pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grimage, &amp; ſhort and tranſitorie life to be gathering of Manna, of ſpiritual food for our ſoules: ſo long as we remain in this world we muſt not be Idle, nor ſéelt for any reſt, vntil our Sabaoth co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth, which is the day of our ioyful reſurrec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, when as with bodie and ſoule wée ſhall remaine in the Kingdome of our Father for euermore, there we ſhal reſt, and then we ſhal reſt, and not before.</p>
            <p>The ſecond cauſe that moued Sathan to make reentrance was, for that hee found his houſe ſwept, and as our Text hath it, it was ſwept with a Beſom.</p>
            <p>A houſe that hath bin long vnſwept and contracted great corruption, it is impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible with a Beſom ſwéeping it to make it cleane, for the dyrt and filth being ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked on the ground, and hardned, is not ſo eaſily taken away, in ſuch a caſe it is neceſſarie and requiſite, that a man vſe the helpe of a paring-knife, or a ſcra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping-iron, for if a man do but ſuperfici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially
<pb facs="tcp:19423:22"/>ſwéepe it with a broome, aſſuredly it will be litle the better. Euen ſo it fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth with the ſoule of a ſinner: how many ſinnes by long continuance haue we contracted in our houſe? how many wayes haue we defiled our ſelues with vile and filthy thoughtes? how many foule and vnſauerie wordes haue wée breathed out of our mouthes, to argue the vncleanes of our Soules within? how many lewd and abominable actes haue we daily committed, and do com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit from time to time? and do we think with a ſleight and ſmall repentance to be pardoned and forgiuen? do we think by knocking once or twice vppon our breaſt, and ſaying, Lord forgiue mee, Lord haue mercie vpon me, our ſinnes ſhall be remitted and taken cleane a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way? What ſhould then that noble king <hi>Ezechias</hi> mean when hée lay ſicke of an infirmitie,<note place="margin">Eſai. 38. v. 10.15.</note> ſo to crie out, and ſay, in the moitie of my yeares, I will deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cend into the graue, and to ſay that hée would call to reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brance all his yeres in the bitternes of his ſoule? What ment the Prophet <hi>Dauid,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 51. v 1.</note> after hee had
<pb facs="tcp:19423:22"/>committed adultery, to crie out, and ſay, Haue mercie on me O God according to thy great mercie? And in another place to ſay, I haue laboured in ſighing,<note place="margin">Pſal. 6. v. 7</note> I ſhal waſh my bed euerie night, and water my Couch with tears. Such and the like ſignes of repentance vſed this noble King and Prophet. What ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of repentance was that of <hi>Magda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len,</hi> when ſhée entered into <hi>Simon</hi> the Pharyſes houſe, bathed our Sauiour his féete with teares,<note place="margin">Luc. 7.</note> and waſhed them with the hairs of her head? O Lord how farre are we in theſe daies from this ſorrow for our ſinnes? We thinke it inough if we crie once vnto the Lord for mercie, we neuer ſtudie to take re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenge of ſinne in our owne fleſh, we are not minded with the Niniuites to repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in Sackcloth and Aſhes,<note place="margin">Ionas 3.6.</note> when as our ſinnes are no leſſe grieuous then theirs, and as many in number, if not more.</p>
            <p>Wée thinke perhaps that Chriſt moc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, when he ſaid: contend yée to enter in at the narrow gate,<note place="margin">Luc. 13.24.</note> for many (I ſay vnto you) ſhal ſéek to enter in &amp; cannot: or that he ſpake not in earneſt when hée
<pb facs="tcp:19423:23"/>ſaid: The Kingdome of Heauen ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth violence, and they that get it, muſt get it by violence. I know not ſurely how we practiſe now a daies to get hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen by viole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, vnleſſe eating and drin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, banqueting, and ſporting, daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, and viſing, ſwearing, and ſtaring, bée violence. If this violence, or the like kinde would get heauen, perhaps a number ſhould come to Heauen, who for vſing the ſame ſhall bée aſſured ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer to come there, but violently to bée thruſt into hel where they ſhal remaine and abide for euermore.</p>
            <p>There be many now a dayes when they are reprehended of ſinne, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded to holines of life, can be content to ſay it is a good thing, it is méete it ſhould be ſo, but to ſtudie as they ſhould amendment of their liues, to plucke ſin by the rootes out of their hart, there are few that will do ſo. Let a man cut his haire neuer ſo ſhorte, yet in ſhort time it wil grow long againe, and why? ſurely there is no other reaſon, but for that the rootes be left in the ſkull ſtil, ſo let vs clip our ſinnes neuer ſo ſhort, and
<pb facs="tcp:19423:23"/>ſwéep our houſes neuer ſo much, vnles wée pluck vp the rootes, and pare away the dirt with a ſharpe paring iron, it will be neuer the better, in ſhort time all thinges will returne vnto their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer lothſomnes againe. And this is the ſecond cauſe or occaſion of the deuils reentrance when he findeth our houſes but ſwept. It followeth,
<q>And he findeth his houſe garniſhed.</q>
            </p>
            <p>This is the third and laſt cauſe that moueth Sathan to make reentrance ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther into man or woman, namely whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he findeth his houſe garniſhed. This garniſhing of the houſe is no more but the corrupt affections and deſire of ſin, which remaine ſtill in the hart of man or woman, although the ſinne be done away, which is an occaſion of returning or falling againe vnto ſinne ſo ſoone as any cauſe of ſinning ſhalbe offered,<note place="margin">1 Thef. 5.23.</note> And therefore Sainct <hi>Paul,</hi> to preuent this miſchiefe, exhorteth vs not onely to ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaine from euil, but from all occaſion or ſhew of euill. For it is not inough for a man to abſtaine from the out ward act of ſinne, vnleſſe he mortifie in himſelfe
<pb facs="tcp:19423:24"/>the inward deſire and affection: for if he entertaine and nouriſh that, no doubt at one time or other he wil come to the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhment, and that is a ſufficient garniſhing for to inuite the Deuill to make a reentrance. A notable example of this matter I may produce out of <hi>Exodus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 10.</note> of <hi>Pharao</hi> King of Egipt, who hauing kept the children of Iſrael a lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g time in his ſubiection, at what time that <hi>Moſes</hi> was ſent by the Lord to moue <hi>Pharao</hi> for their departure out of his Countrey, vnto the deſert, <hi>Pharao</hi> bée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing loth to forgoe ſo great a multitude, whom he vſed as ſlaues in al ſeruile la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hours, reſiſted a long time, vntil at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> laſt being terrified by ſundrie plagues that the Lord ſent vpon him, he called <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi> vnto him in the end, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. <hi>Ite &amp; ſacrificate Domino Deo ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtro, oues tantum veſtrae, &amp; armen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta remaneant, paruuli veſtri eant vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſcum,</hi> Go yée (ſaith hée) and ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice yée vnto the Lord your God, &amp; take your litle Children with you. Let onely your ſhéepe and cattel remaine behind. What was <hi>Pharaos</hi> meaning in this,
<pb facs="tcp:19423:24"/>thinke you? Had he ſuch a deſire of the ſhéepe and cattell that he eſtéemed them more then the Iſraelites themſelues? no verilie, he was a Prince and a King, and of the Iſraelites goods he ſtood in no néede, but he had a farder meaning and that was this, he thought the Iſraelites had couetous mindes, and that when they ſhould come into the deſert, and finde the want of neceſſarie prouiſion, and bee pinched with penurie, they ſhoulde remember their Cattell that they left behinde them in Egypt, and thereby bee mooued to come backe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, the which <hi>Pharao</hi> thought hée might eaſily bring to paſſe, if he might reſerue ſtill in his handes, but ſuch a pawne.</p>
            <p>This was the drift and purpoſe of <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rao:</hi> euen ſo it fareth with Sathan and a ſinner, the ſinner whom Sathan a long time hath had in ſubiection, if by <hi>Moſes</hi> &amp; <hi>Aaron</hi> he be commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part out of Egipt, that is, if by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers of Gods word be moued to forſake his ſinne, and to trauell into the deſert of repentance, Sathan is loth he ſhould
<pb facs="tcp:19423:25"/>goe, and hardly he will let him depart, vnleſſe the Lord do plague Sathan, that is by giuing ſuch grace and ſtrength vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ſinner, that maugre Sathans ſpight, he will deſiſt from ſinne, he will frame himſelfe vnto an exchange of life, hee will frequent the Church, he are Gods word, read Gods word, conuerſe amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g good &amp; godlie perſons of whom he may be inſtructed, learned, and taught: all which thinges although Sathan bee loth he ſhould do, as by experience each of vs may finde in our ſelues how loth Sathan is that we ſhould ſerue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord, or be at any time wel &amp; vertuouſly occu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pied, and layeth all the impedimentes and blockes in our way that he can to make vs deſiſt and leaue of our good purpoſe and intent, yet (I ſay) when he ſeeth there is no other remedy, but that the grace of the Lord is ſo ſtrong in vs that we break the Deuils bonds a ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and that we releaſe our ſelues out of his bo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dage whether hée wil or not, he can be content then with <hi>Pharao</hi> to ſay. <hi>Ite, &amp; ſacrificate Domino Deo ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtro. &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:19423:25"/>
            <p>Goe yée, and Sacrifice yée vnto the Lord your God, hee can bee content we ſhould come to the Church, hear the word preached, read it at home in our houſes, talke of it at our tables, and the like: onely he craueth at our handes but a pawn, that is, that we leaue our ſhéep and cattell behinde vs with him in kée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, that is, that we retayne ſtill but the affection and deſire of ſinne, that wée would retaine but in our memorie the pleaſures that we had in the world, that when we are in the deſert, the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> turpitudes of our fleſh, may bring vs backe againe as <hi>S. Peter</hi> ſayth like dogges vnto our vomits.<note place="margin">2 Pet. 2.22</note>
            </p>
            <p>But (derely beloued) in this caſe we muſt anſwere Satha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as <hi>Moſes</hi> anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red <hi>Pharao, Cuncti greges pergent no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſcum: non remanebit ex eis vngula.</hi> All our cattel ſhal goe with vs, we wil not leaue behind vs ſo much as an hoof. So muſt wée anſwere the Deuil in the act of our repentance, that wee wil re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne vnto the Lord with al our hartes, with all our mindes, with al our ſoules, we will ſerue him with our bodies,
<pb facs="tcp:19423:26"/>liues and goodes, all our cattel, that is, all our deſires and affections ſhall goe with vs, we will not leaue ſo much as a hoofe in the world, ſo much as a deſire to returne backe againe vnto ſin, which we purpoſe to forſake, vnleſſe it happen to vs as it happened vuto <hi>Lots</hi> wife,<note place="margin">Ge. 19.26</note> to be transformed into a ſalt ſtone. Who ſoeuer ſhall do this, hee ſhall kéepe his ſoule vngarniſhed, and the Deuil by that occaſion ſhall neuer finde means to make reentra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, the which the Lord for his mercy grant vs grace that we may performe. And thus much of the ſecond part which was the returne of Sathan to make a repoſſeſſion, and the cauſes y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moued him vnto the ſame.</p>
            <p>Now it followeth to ſhew that when Sathan being returned,<note place="margin">Pars. 3.</note> and finding his houſe, as I ſaid, emptie, ſwept, and gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, how he taketh poſſeſſion and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereth in more ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gly then euer he did before, and therefore thus it followeth in the text.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Then goeth hee and taketh ſeauen ſpirites worſe then himſelfe, and they enter in and dwell there.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:19423:26"/>
            <p>Now are we come to the repoſſeſſion of the enemie, whereby we haue to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, that that man or woman that hath receiued Gods grace, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward falleth vnto his former accuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med wicked life, that man or woman doth giue the Deuil an occaſion to make a reentrie, and comming againe he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth with an army of other ſeauen ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits worſe then himſelfe, and they al en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in and dwel there.<note place="margin">2 Pet. 2.21.</note> Oh better had it bin (as <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith) neuer to haue knowen the way of righteouſnes, then after a man hath knowen it, to turne from the holy commaundement that was giuen vnto him.<note place="margin">Hebr. 10.26.</note> And as the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle <hi>Paul</hi> witneſſeth, if we ſinne wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly, after that we haue receiued the knowledge of the truth, there remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth no more ſacrifice for ſinnes but a fearefull looking for of iudgement, and violent fire, which ſhall deuour the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſaries. Let vs take héede therefore derely beloued, how wee behaue our ſelues after that we haue receiued the grace of God, leaſt for our ingratitude &amp; negligence, our Candleſticke be remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued,<note place="margin">Apoc. 2.7.</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:19423:27"/>&amp; our grace taken from vs &amp; giuen to an other that ſhall bring forth better fruite. To come to my Text, that it is ſaid, that he taketh ſeauen ſpirits worſe then him ſelfe, they are counted worſe, in that they come furniſhed with grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter malice to ſéeke the deſtruction of the ſoule of man. In that he nameth a nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of <hi>7.</hi> I ſuppoſe the Euangeliſt mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth a number of perfection, that is to to wit, the Deuil returneth with an ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute power, for vnder this number <hi>7.</hi> all power that the Deuil can vſe is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teined. So we reade that <hi>Marie Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalene</hi> was poſſeſſed with <hi>7.</hi> ſpirites, &amp; that our Sauiour caſt out of her ſeauen Deuils,<note place="margin">Luc, 8.2.3</note> which ſignifyeth al kind of ſin. So that the number of <hi>7.</hi> importeth that Sathan if he come back and repoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſe either man or woman againe, hee will omitte no occaſion to hinder them that they ſhall neuer returne vnto God againe, and therefore the matter is moſt daungerous and diligently to bee looked vnto. And where it is ſaid in our text that all theſe ſpirites doe enter in and dwel there. You muſt vnderſtand
<pb facs="tcp:19423:27"/>how and in what maner the deuild wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth in a bodie, he doth not dwell as the Philoſophers ſay, <hi>tanquam corpus lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in loco,</hi> as a body placed in a place for the Deuils are ſpirites, and not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teined in any place. Nor yet <hi>tanquam forma in materia,</hi> as the ſoule of a man doth dwell in a bodie. For the Deuil is a ſimple ſubſtance of himſelfe, and not compoſed or ioyned to any matter, but the Deuils dwelling is onely by his power or operation: where he hath po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, there he exercyſeth his ſtrength, &amp; there he is ſaid to dwel. The Lord defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d vs from his power, and that he dwell not ſo among vs.</p>
            <p>I haue bin too long I feare me in my former partes, I wil now haſten to the fourth and laſt part, &amp; ſo make an end. It followeth in the text.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And the laſt ſtate of that man is worſe then the firſt.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pars 4.</note>
            </p>
            <p>This is the fourth part of my diuiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on wherein I am to ſhew, how that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a man hath receiued the grace of God and that the foule &amp; vnclean ſpirit y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> led and tempted him to al wickednes
<pb facs="tcp:19423:28"/>by the greate mercie of God was caſt out of him, if after he loke not wel vnto himſelfe, auoiding as nere as he can all occaſions and cauſes of ſin, but leauing his houſe emptie, that is, his ſoule void of a true faith, and good workes, &amp; that for all his abhominable ſinnes that hee hath committed, hée hath but ſwept his houſe, that is, made a ſuperficial ſorow or repentance for his ſinnes, and that which is worſe, leaueth his houſe gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, that is, retaineth ſtil the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance, deſire, &amp; affection of his former concupiſcence: vnto ſuch a man Sathan doth ſone returne againe, and in retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning he bringeth ſeauen worſe ſpirites then himſelfe, and they enter in and dwel there, then it can not be, according vnto our Sauiòur his teſtimonie, but that the end of that man muſt bée worſe then his beginning.</p>
            <p>Wherefore that you may vnderſtand how much worſe the ſtate of that man ſhall be in the end, it ſhall not be amiſſe if you know how bad the eſtate of a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner is in the beginning. And that you may the better iudge of the vilenes and
<pb facs="tcp:19423:28"/>deformitie of the firſt ſinne I know not which way I may make you to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d it better then to lay before your eies the excellencie of vertue. For eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thing (as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Philoſopher ſaith) is beſt knowen being compared by his contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie. What man is he that can tel the commoditie of health ſo well as he that hath bin afflicted w<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſicknes? or who kno<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>weth ſo wel the ſwéetnes of libertie as he that hath had experie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of captiuity? To know therefore the vilenes of an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uil thing, we muſt conſider the nature and condition of a good thing, for the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formitie of a crooked line will appeare beſt if it be meaſured by a right rule or ſquare. The Philoſophers defyned that there was nothing that could bée good which had not all, or at leaſt one of theſe thrée properties, that is, if it were not honeſt, profitable, or delightfull, and although the wiſer ſort of them deſined certainly, that nothing could bee good that was not honeſt, yet y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thing which in his owne nature is not honeſt, if it be either delightfull or profitable, it carieth at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> leaſt a reſemblance of good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes.
<pb facs="tcp:19423:29"/>And thereof it commeth, that no man would committe any ſinne, but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> it caryeth ſome ſhew of goodnes: for al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though ſyn in the iudgement of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitter bee no honeſt thing, yet he iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth it at the leaſt to be either profitable or delightfull, or elſe hée would neuer do it. The fornicatour or adulterer he knoweth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſinnes of the fleſh, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they are not honeſt, yet he thinketh them delite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full. The vſurer or couetous man he knoweth, that briberie and extortion is nought and not honeſt, yet he thinketh it profitable. So that I ſay, euerie ſin that the ſinner commiteth, he doth it vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the colour of ſome good, or elſe hee would neuer do it. Goodnes therefore in it ſelfe ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not be but an excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t thing. And looke how much the more it doth participate of all the thrée properties y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is to wit, honeſty, profite, and delight, ſo much better it muſt be. Vertue ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is an excellent thing, for it is both honeſt, profitable, and delightfull. And that thing what ſoeuer it be that is moſt honeſt, moſt profitable, and moſt delite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, muſt néedes be moſt excellent &amp; be
<pb facs="tcp:19423:29"/>that which is called <hi>Summum bonum,</hi> the chiefeſt good, which all men natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally do deſire. And who is moſt honeſt, moſt profitable, and moſt delightful, but onely God: God therefore is <hi>ſummum bonum,</hi> the end that euerie man ought to ſéek, and ſuch an end, that he that fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth it ſhall be bleſſed for euermore.</p>
            <p>Now at the laſt wee haue found out our rule and ſquare of goodnes to mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure the crokedneſſe of vice, and to ſée the deformity thereof. As the thing that is moſt honeſt, moſt profitable, &amp; moſt delightful is moſt good. That thing that is oppoſite and contrarie vnto the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt good, muſt néedes be the greateſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill. That thing that depriueth a man or woman from the greateſt good of all other, which is God, muſt néedes be the greateſt of all euils, and that euil is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led ſinne: for ſin depriueth a man of the chiefeſt good, which is God, and therfore ſinne muſt be the greateſt euill of all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Will you ſée how ſin is oppoſite and contrarie vnto the thrée properties of good, (and ſo by conſequence vnto God) namely vnto honeſtie, profite, and
<pb facs="tcp:19423:30"/>delite, then giue you me leaue a litle to examine each propertie apart, and with patience and attention harken what I ſhal ſay.</p>
            <p>Firſt of all, Sin, as the Philoſophers define it, being no poſitiue thing but a priuation or taking away, it is as much to ſay, it hath in it nothing that is good, but taketh from a man all that is good. And the chiefeſt property wherein good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes conſiſteth, and without the which there can indéede be no goodnes, is ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtie, and that ſinne depriueth a man of, for ſin in his owne nature is ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and oppoſit vnto honeſty, in ſo much as it is written, <hi>Qui malè agit, odit lucem.</hi> He that doth euil, he hateth the light. Sinne is a worke of darknes, it feareth to be ſéene, it is loth to come to the light, it ſéeketh darke places, and ſecret corners. Examples of this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter we haue great ſtore; euerie man can witnes it in his own conſcience. <hi>Adam</hi> ſo ſéene as he had ſinned in Paradice,<note place="margin">Gen. 3.</note> &amp; that he ſawe himſelfe to be naked, was he not aſhamed? did he not hide himſelfe from the preſence of the Lord? What
<pb facs="tcp:19423:30"/>ſhall we ſay of <hi>Dauid,</hi> that after he had committed adultery with <hi>Bethſabe,</hi> in ſending for <hi>Vrias</hi> home, in procuring him to goe home to fléepe with his wife, in giuing him meat and drinke apt for that purpoſe, was it for any other thing but that he was aſhamed of his fact, he would faine haue had the matter coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, but it would not bee, the Lord did bolt it out, ſending <hi>Nathan</hi> the Prophet to him, who reprehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded him of his falt,<note place="margin">2 Sam. 11.</note> then hee could crye, <hi>Peccatum meum coram me eſt ſe mper,</hi> My ſinne is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies in my ſight,<note place="margin">Pſal. 51.</note> I am aſhamed O Lord of that which I haue done. This may you ſée how oppoſite a thing ſinne is vnto honeſtie, that it bringeth with it nothing elſe but confuſion and ſhame.</p>
            <p>Let vs now ſée how it contrarieth the ſecond propertie of goodnes, which is profite. How vnprofitable a thing ſinne is.</p>
            <p>To ſpeake of the diſprofite that ſin bringeth, if I ſhould ſay ſo much as might be ſayd I ſhould neuer make an end, what greater diſprofite can it be to a man or woman, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to looſe their ſoule
<pb facs="tcp:19423:31"/>eternally. In ſo much as our Sauiour him ſelfe ſaieth:<note place="margin">Mat. 16.26.</note> What ſhall it profit a man to haue gayned the whole worlde and after ſhall ſuſtaine the loſſe of his ſoule? or what exchaunge or commuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion can a man make for his ſoul? Shall I bréefly diſcurre vnto you, what loſſe ſin did bring? Note firſt in the Aungels them ſelues,<note place="margin">Gen. 1.</note> who for ſinne were depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued for euer from the viſion of God, and are now damned for euermore.</p>
            <p>For ſinne <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eue</hi> were exyled Paradice,<note place="margin">Gen. 3.</note> and al their poſteritie made ſubiect to death &amp; miſerie. For ſinne the whole world was drowned,<note place="margin">Gen. 7.</note> 
               <hi>8.</hi> perſons excepted. For ſinne Sodom and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morrha with other Cities there adia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent were conſumed and burnt by fire,<note place="margin">Gen. 19.</note> and all the people periſhed. For ſinne the Children of Iſraell were caried twiſe captiue,<note place="margin">2 Reg. 17.</note> once vnder <hi>Salmanaſar</hi> king of the Aſſirians, and an other time vnder <hi>Nabuchodonoſor</hi> king of Babi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon, beſides a number other plagues and loſſes y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> came to them through ſin.<note place="margin">2 Reg. 25.</note> Finallie ſinne brought ſuch a loſſe vnto mankinde, as the raunſome therof was
<pb facs="tcp:19423:31"/>neuer able to be paied, but by the death and paſſion of Ieſus Chriſt, the onely ſonne of the liuing God.</p>
            <p>Let this at this time ſuffice for the loſſe or diſprofit that commeth vnto ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or woman by ſinne. Perhaps this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter or loſſe may be requited with the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lite that ſinne bringeth with it, and ſo great may be the delite y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> a man careth neither for honeſtie nor profit. If it bee ſo, then let vs conſider the delite that ſin bringeth a part, and ſée what is the pleaſure that a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> receiueth in the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting of ſinne. And that is the third property of goodnes that I haue to ſpeak of, namely delite. And now ſhall you ſée how oppoſite a thing ſin is vnto delite alſo.</p>
            <p>Sinne (as I ſaid) is a thing oppoſite vnto that part of good which is called delight, for it is a moſt ſad and ſorrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full euil full of griefe and penſiuenes. Sin is ſo ſad and penſiue a thing, that it doth not onely bring a man vnto eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall death, but it leaueth a man full of trouble and griefe alſo in this life.</p>
            <p>The iuſtice of God can not ſuffer the
<pb facs="tcp:19423:32"/>guilt of ſin to be vnpuniſhed. And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Prophet <hi>Ieremie</hi> gaue vs to vnderſtand y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> euil of ſinne in this point,<note place="margin">Ier. 8.</note> when he ſaid. Know thou, and ſée how euill and bitter a thing it is to haue for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken the Lord thy God. For beſides y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> eternall and euerlaſting puniſhment which excéedeth al other puniſhmentes, and I haue no leiſure to ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to diſcourſe vpon at this time, I wil reckon vp four greate euils that it bringeth vnto a man or woman in this life, which no man what ſoeuer hee bee, can by any means auoid.</p>
            <p>The firſt is the ſting of a mans con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience which hee hath pricking within after he hath committed the ſinne. Of al other thinges how ſwéete ſoeuer ſin ſée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth in the beginning, it hath the vileſt end, yea ſuch an ende, that it bringeth many a man or woman vnto deſperati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on after they haue committed a wicked fact. When a man hath ſatisfyed his fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy luſt, what lothſomnes doth he finde remaining in his ſoule and conſcience? a fitter example I cannot giue you, then <hi>Amon Dauids</hi> ſonne, who falling in
<pb facs="tcp:19423:32"/>loue with his Siſter <hi>Thamar</hi> in ſuch wiſe,<note place="margin">2 Sam. 13</note> as he almoſt periſhed for loue and luſt, yet when he had accompliſhed his will and purpoſe, there remained ſuch a lothſomnes behind of ſinne that he could neuer abide to looke vpon <hi>Thamar</hi> after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward. And this I dare be bold to ſay, that there is no ſinner aliue, let him bée neuer ſo ſhameleſſe and impudent in his ſinne, let him face and braue it out with neuer ſo deſperate a minde, yet he can not ſo extinguiſh that touch of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, but his ſoule at one time or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhall finde the torment of the ſame.</p>
            <p>The ſecond euill that ſinne bringeth to a man or woman to contrarie delite, is ſhame: of the which, for that I haue touched it alreadie, I wil ſpare to ſpeak any more of it, but come vnto the Text.</p>
            <p>The third euil that ſinne bringeth in this life to contrarie delight, is feare of puniſhment, for the ſinfull man after he hath committed a naughtie fact, he is by and by afraid. Hee knoweth ther is a God aboue that wil reuenge all ſinne, and he is afeard of Gods iudgementes, and of ſodeine death. This feare remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth
<pb facs="tcp:19423:33"/>of inferiour Magiſtrates that are adminiſters of Gods iuſtice. For if a Théefe after he haue committed a robe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie be brought before a Iuſtice to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amined forthwith he feareth, and faul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereth in his ſpéech &amp; anſwers, &amp; a guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie conſcience bewrayeth it ſelfe, ſo that he that ſinneth is alwayes fearfull, and as <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Prou. 28.1.</note> the wicked man hée fléeth when no man perſecuteth him.</p>
            <p>In ſo much as ſinne is a continuall hangman that tormenteth a mans con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience where ſo euer he goeth.</p>
            <p>The fourth and laſt euill that ſinne bringeth contrarie to delight, is a conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall combat and conflicte betweene reaſon and ſenſualitie. In ſo much as when ſenſualitie entiſeth vs to a thing that is naught, reaſon ſayth, do it not, ſenſualitie ſaith, do it. And ſuch a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trariety a man ſhal find in him ſelf, that oft times he is forced to crie out, and ſay with <hi>Iob. Factus ſum mihimetipſi gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uis,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iob. 7.20.</note> I am become troubleſome vnto my ſelfe.</p>
            <p>Thus haue I made a briefe deſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the vilenes and crookednes of
<pb facs="tcp:19423:33"/>ſinne, which if it be laied to the right rule of goodnes that is honeſty, profit, and delite: You may ſée how vile a thing it is, and far from all goodnes, that hath in it neither honeſtie, profit, nor delite. And depriuing a man of all honeſtie, profite, and delite, which is the greateſt good y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> may be, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in God himſelfe, from who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſin ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludeth vs. Alſo it cannot be but wee muſt neceſſarilie conclude, that ſin is the greateſt euil that may be, and that there is no euill to be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pared or mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched with ſin.</p>
            <p>Thus hauing found out the vilenes of the firſt euill, it reſteth that wee know how the ſeconde euill may bee worſe then this, for that it is ſaid in our text. The laſt ſtate of that man is worſe then the firſt. A man would thinke that the firſt is ſo bad, as light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly there could be no worſe: but how the laſt becommeth worſe then the firſt, in few wordes I ſhall ſhew. If we reſpect ſin in his owne nature, it is alwaies euill &amp; ſo euil, as it can
<pb facs="tcp:19423:34"/>not be worſe. But if we reſpect it as it is renued in action, the more an ill thing is renued, the worſe ſtil it is, by reaſon of the ingratitude that remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth in the offender. As for example. A man committing a treſpaſſe once, he is pardoned of his Prince, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitteth the ſame offence again in the ſame nature, both the offences in their own nature are bad, and nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther worſe then the other, but in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the ingratitude of the offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, who being pardoned once, would not take héede the ſecond time. And ſo foorth of all other ſinnes that ſo ſhal be renewed, the more they are renewed the more hainons they are by reaſon of the ingratitude.</p>
            <p>Now where our Text ſayth, that the laſt ſtate of ſuch a one ſhall bee worſe then the firſt, I will ſhew you briefly alſo how y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> may be ment, and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> is for thrée reſpects. Firſt in reſpect of the Deuil that tempteth a man to ſin. Secondly in reſpect of the offender that committeth the ſinne. Thirdly
<pb facs="tcp:19423:34"/>in reſpect of God that puniſheth ſin. All theſe I ſhall make plaine by a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliar example. And firſt in reſpect of the Deuil that tempteth vnto ſinne. I will ſhew you how the laſt euill is worſe then the firſt. Take the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of a Iaylour that taketh a man to priſon, the man being committed but for debt, or ſome ſuch other treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe, is indifferently wel vſed, and entreated in Priſon, he hath as much libertie as the Priſon can yéeld him, and as much fauour as the Iailour can ſhew him: But if this Priſoner watching his oportunitie, do happen to breake forth, and to make an eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cape, how doth the Iaylour then rage and fume, and how doth he threaten and lay about him, ſaying that if euer he catch that Priſoner againe, hee will vſe him, and ſo forth. So as you ſée, it ſtandeth the Priſoner vppon that is ſo broken away, to looke vnto himſelfe, for otherwiſe it had bin bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for him that hee had remained in Priſon ſtill, and made no eſcape. It
<pb facs="tcp:19423:35"/>commeth to paſſe that he is taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, how is this poore wretch then vſed, hee is layed in Boltes, he is kept vnder locke and key, hee goeth not out of his chamber, he is continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally watched, you ſée how his laſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonment is worſe then the firſt, by reaſon of the cruell vſage of the Iay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour. Euen ſo it fareth with a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, who as long as he is in ſinne, is in the Deuils kéeping, and ſo long as he continueth in ſinne, the Deuil let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth him alone, doth not trouble him much, but letteth him enioy the liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the Priſon, that is the pleaſures of this world, and ſuffreth him to goe from one to an other without contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction. But if this ſinner chaunce at any time to be moued by grace to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake ſinne, and the pleaſures of this world, and to breake priſon, that is to giue the Deuill the ſlippe, and meaneth to returne to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſeruice of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie God; it ſtandeth this man vppon to looke well vnto himſelfe, and to thinke that the Deuil hath a conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall
<pb facs="tcp:19423:35"/>eye vpon him, and if euer hee can catch him againe, and bring him within the compaſſe of his Priſon, let him be aſſured he wil kéepe him more warely the ſecond time, and remoue from him al the occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s that brought him to goodnes, and locke him vp faſt in a cloſe dungeon, where hee ſhall ſée nothing, and féele nothing but conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall temptations and allurements vnto ſinne, and ſhall be ſo watched &amp; guarded that he ſhal hardly make any eſcape againe. And thus you ſée how the ſecond eſtate of a ſinner is worſe then the firſt, in reſpect of the Deuill by compariſon of a Iailour.</p>
            <p>The laſt eſtate of a Sinner is worſe then the firſt alſo in reſpect of the ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner himſelfe; for experience and natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral reaſon teacheth, that many actions do at the laſt come to bee an habit, and long cuſtome in any thing doth alter nature, wherefore that man or wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man that frequenteth much ſynning, in time can come to do nothing els.</p>
            <p>Wee ſee by daily experience that a
<pb facs="tcp:19423:36"/>Childe that hath bin vertuouſlie or wel brought vp when he commeth to yeares, and beginneth to ſee the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions of the world, how at firſt not being experienced with the filthines of ſinne, he accounteth it an abhomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable thing, but if after hee fall into ill companie, among whom ſynne is boldlie vſed, by litle and litle he may be drawen to commit it once: If hée haue committed ſinne one time, hee wil be the more eaſyly drawen to the ſecond, and ſo to the third, and at laſt he wil be as bold in ſynne as the beſt, and as ſhameleſſe as the reſt.</p>
            <p>And thus you ſe how the laſt ſtate of a ſinner is worſe then the firſt, by reaſon of the Synner himſelfe.</p>
            <p>Finallie the laſt ſtate of a ſynner is worſe then the firſt in reſpect of God who puniſheth ſynne. For the order of iuſtice requireth that the more gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and benefits that a man receiueth at the Lordes handes, and the more he conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>neth and abuſeth them, that the more ſeuere and gréeuous ſhall be
<pb facs="tcp:19423:36"/>his puniſhment. And therefore it ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth euerie man and woman vpon to take héed that he receiue not the grace of God in vaine. That we abuſe not Gods mercy by adding now ſinnes to our old. For as the Apoſtle ſayth,<note place="margin">Rom. 2.4.</note> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Lord is mercifull, patient &amp; long ſuffering: ſhall wee therefore make this an occaſion of ſinne, God forbid. I denie not but in what ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer ſoeuer a ſinner ſhall repent and turne fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his wicked waies, that the Lord will receiue &amp; take him to mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, if he repent indéede from his hart and haue a full purpoſe by the helpe &amp; aſſiſtance of Gods grace to ſinne no more: the which purpoſe and intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on if the ſinner haue not, and when he hath it, vnleſſe he put in practiſe, and execute it, his repentance is no repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, hee doth but dallye and mocke with God Almightie, hee feareth not his iudgements, and therefore he ſhall neuer be partaker of his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie.</p>
            <p>And thus ye ſée how the laſt eſtate of
<pb facs="tcp:19423:37"/>a ſinner is worſe then the firſt in reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect of God himſelfe. The concluſion of the whole is this.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>So ſhal it bee with this wicked gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By theſe wordes we may perceiue that our Sauiour Chriſt ment that, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hath bin ſpoken, of the Scribes and Phariſes, who contemned and malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned him for all his miracles and won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders that he wrought among them.</p>
            <p>Let vs (déerly beloued) for our profit and benefit apply them to our ſelues, and thinke that they are ſpoken vnto euery one of vs here in particular: let vs not abuſe the graces and mercies that the Lord hath beſtowed among vs, as the Scribes and Phariſes did, leaſt according to the example of the repoſſeſſed man, we be accounted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong that wicked and peruerſe gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration.</p>
            <p>If I ſhould reckon vnto you the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefites and graces wherwith y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord hath bleſſed our Countrie, and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue other nations, I ſhould hold you
<pb facs="tcp:19423:37"/>ouer long. Of an infinit number take a few, and beſides the common bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits note the particular, and ſo I make and end. We were al poſſeſſed with the Spirit of blindneſſe as all other natio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s who tempted vs to al vnclean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, to Idolatrie and ſuperſtition, in as vile and as wicked maner as euer the Gentiles or Pagans were.</p>
            <p>It pleaſed the Lord to expell this ſpirite of darknes from vs, and to ſend vs the light of his Goſpel by the which hee hath illumined vs, that there is no nation at this day vnder heauen that hath it more bright. Hee hath ſent vs beſides a moſt gratious Quéene and Prince, vnder whoſe moſt happie gouernment we haue li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued theſe <hi>30,</hi> yeares in great peace &amp; tranquillitie more then any Nation round about vs: he hath mightily &amp; miraculouſly defended both her and vs from the inuaſion of our enemies that thought to haue ſwallowed and deuoured vs vp quicke. What ſhall I ſay, what mercy hath he not ſhewed
<pb facs="tcp:19423:38"/>vs, what wonders hath hee not wrought amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt vs. And yet behold, are we not become almoſt vnmindful of theſe benefits? do we not abuſe theſe mercies of almighty god in promiſing vnto our ſelues peace &amp; ſecuritie, and thereby remain in our former ſinnes and wickednes? Bee our liues any thing amended, our manners and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauiours bettered, whereby the Lord may bee the more glorified, and our ſelues comforted? I feare me no; How doth ſin abound yet amongſt vs? how doth euerie one walke after his owne wicked concupiſcence? How doth ſin ſhew herſelfe almoſt with vncouered face? If I ſhould enter into the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars, I ſhould amaze you. Pride aboundeth, lecherie ouerfloweth, coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſnes rageth, and not in any ſmall portion, but in <hi>ſummo gradu,</hi> in the higheſt degrée. Is it not to be feared, if it ſo continue, but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> the vncleane ſpirit wil returne againe: and y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> if hée come, do you not thinke that hee will bring ſeauen worſe then himſelf, and that
<pb facs="tcp:19423:38"/>God for our vnworthines wil permit him to make ree<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce? So ſhould our end be worſe than the beginning. So ſhould we haue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> maledictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked generation. That y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wrath of the Lord may be auerted fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs, in this I can ſay no more, but repent &amp; amend, for the day of the Lord is at ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d. For the which y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord gra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t vs all grace to prepare our ſelues to be in a redines.</p>
            <p>But for as much as no man is able to make this preparation of himſelfe without the eſpeciall grace of God, let vs with humble and penitent hartes craue of our heauenly Father for his Sonne our Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt his ſake, that hee would vouchſafe of his infinite goodnes and mercie to take from vs our ſtonie hartes, and put in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs fleſhy hartes, that may bee pliable vnto his holye will, and ſo to be gouerned by his holie Spirite, that in al the aſſaultes of our enemie, he may haue no power ouer vs, but that by his power and might we may vanquiſh and ouercome him, and that we
<pb facs="tcp:19423:39"/>may be ſo fortifyed, that no aduerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie put vs downe, no proſperite puffe vs vp, and that on euery ſide wée be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing fenced by the Lords moſt heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly protection, Sathan that goeth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout like a roring Lion ſéeking whom hee may deuour, may make no reen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try. Graunt this O heauenly Father for thy deare ſonne Ieſus Chriſt his ſake, together with the holy ſpirite. To whom being thrée Perſons in Trinitie and one in vnitie be all glorie, praiſe, power and dominio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> both now and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uermore.</p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <pb facs="tcp:19423:39"/>
            <p>Imprinted at London by <hi>Iohn Windet, dwelling at the</hi> Signe of the Cros-keies, by Paules wharfe.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
